JASON BARNES, MBA

Quantico, VA 951-293-3849

Barnes7599@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/j-barnes/

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Self-directed, multi-disciplinary designer with a strong visual design approach and a proven history of turning large data sets into progressive ideas through the creation of clear, compelling infographics, maps, data visualizations, interactive media and product designs. Specialize in presenting to senior level executives, data storytelling, managing cross-functional projects and leading teams. Career supported by Master of Business Administration and Master of Professional Studies in Data Analytics and Visualization.

- Program Management
- Leadership
- Data Analysis

- Financial Management
- People Analytics
- Data Visualization
- Personnel Management
- Tableau, R, SQL
- Jira

EDUCATION

Master's in Data Analytics and Visualization, Maryland Institute College of Arts (MICA) - 2021 Customer Analytics, Executive Education, The Wharton School - 2019 Master of Business Administration (MBA), Naval Postgraduate School - 2014 Bachelor of Science, Criminal Justice, Law Enforcement, Park University – 2005

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

CACI International, Quantico, VA Senior Business Intelligence and Data Visualization Engineer

2019-Present

Led an interdisciplinary team of 10 interactive data visualization designers, developers, product managers, and product owners in a fast-paced, agile environment for the Department of Veteran Affairs -National Cemetery Administration.

- Responsible for managing, designing, implementing and customizing interactive infographics, reports and dashboards for three executive directors, five district administrators, 147 cemetery managers and over 500 business analysts.
- Managed the technical specifications in order to translate product concepts and wireframes into sophisticated, creative, and visually engaging designs and data visualizations for the creation of 8 executive Tableau dashboards.
- Provided leadership in the development and support of reporting solutions including program modifications, performance tuning, problem solving, debugging, and unit testing.
- Orchestrated and designed, innovative and automated solutions that use data and analytics to meet our current and future business needs and are deployable at scale.
- Designed and developed the Visual and Data Visualization Style Guide enabling the department to maintain and apply a unified look and feel across products including fonts, colors, iconography, and imagery.
- Led the development of visual analytical applications from wireframe and storyboards to complete production-ready applications.
- Managed multiple initiatives from assessing business needs, translating complex data logic and technical requirements to design implementation, and gathering feedback from end users.
- Successfully managed the migration of 8 production dashboards to Amazon Web Service (AWS) Oracle

Instance resulting in near-real time information sharing.

United States Marine Corps, Quantico, VA Head Business Analytics, Manpower Fiscal and Entitlements

2016 - 2019

Managed risk upon multiple lines to lead 12 cross-functional human resource, information technology and financial analysts; Responsible for integration, enablement, analysis and KPI frameworks for data driven enhancements to personnel relocation data. Advised senior business partners on data informed decision strategies to meet organizational objectives.

- Managed crosscutting manpower relocation projects and system support changes directly resulting in \$30M savings over a three-year period.
- Created a team culture of cross-functional analysts to prioritize organizational vision and strategies leading to new methods of conducting people analytics that identifies trends, solves complex problems, and optimizes system processes.
- Analyzed large and complex multi-year personnel data using business analytics software to inform strategic plans and solutions for complex business objectives.
- Skillfully provided trend analysis and graphical representation of business unit success through developed KPIs across the human resource development process generating executive insight and financial planning of critical programs.
- Developed a customer propensity model to inform strategic management initiatives resulting in an organizational shift in global policy and execution practices for 16,000 personnel overseas.
- Developed and led a proof of concept strategy for business intelligence software, included R Server, Tableau desktop and Tableau server leading to the creation of organization wide real-time dashboards and business intelligence tools best practices.

United States Marine Corps, Quantico, VA Budget and Execution Program Manager, Manpower Management

2014 - 2016

Managed fiscal entitlements and program operations related to analytics, forecasting, budgeting and execution of personnel relocation funding in excess of \$450M annually.

- Managed infrastructure changes to personnel support systems and engineering change proposals to enhance the accuracy of fiscal obligations as it relates to personnel relocation.
- Expertly created an integrated and balanced budget strategy resulting in resource allocations for Future Years Defense Program of over \$2.5B.
- Developed a systematic process that resulted in more efficient methodologies of collecting, recording and processing over \$900K pay entitlements and saving 1,040 man-hours over a 4-year period.
- Managed cross-cutting manpower spending accounts for eight branches over \$2.1M annually in fiscal resources resulting in an uninterrupted operational travel requirement.

Marine Aircraft Group, Miramar, CA F/A-18D Pilot, Communications, Advanced Life Support Systems

2009 - 2013

Managed a diverse workforce of 25 civilian and military personnel in multiple areas of operational support to include embarkation and logistics, communications and life support systems. Led flight crews on numerous high-risk flight missions utilizing critical thinking, training and situational awareness to safely conduct operations and ensure mission accomplishment.

- Planned, coordinated and managed the technical specification requirements in development of Video Teleconferencing (VTC) conference room contract of \$200K directly contributing to improved communications to outside agencies, ultimately saving \$350K annually in travel expenses.
- Refined the communication network via updated tracking software contributing to over 800 mishap free flights, directly translating to higher readiness rates and cost avoidance.
- Coordinated with multiple agencies, directed and managed the movement of 187 personnel and 71 tons of cargo over a distance of 8700 miles; expert logistics acumen led to the safe and timely arrival of all personnel and equipment allowing for immediate employment of critical assets.
- Led coordination efforts between fiscal, maintenance, administration and heavy equipment support service representatives to ensure all routine and unforeseen logistical duties were completed on time and under budget.

AWARDS

Class standing at Officer Candidate School was 8 of 141 with a final academic overall average of 94.5%, recipient of Commanding Officers top 10% award.

Class standing at the Officers Basic School was 6 of 243 with a final academic overall average of 94.4%, recipient of Commanding Officers top 10% award.

Class standing at Advanced Jet Course was 1 of 22 with a final academic overall average of 97.6%, recipient of the "Golden Stick Award" (Top of class achievement).

PUBLICATIONS

DRIVERS OF TURNOVER AND AFFILIATION IN THE UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS RESERVES (2015) Western Academy of Management Conference, Kauai, HI Authors: Marco DiRenzo PhD, Kathryn Aten PhD, Jason Barnes MBA, Adam Shapiro MBA, Benny Volkmann P.E.

CERTIFICATIONS AND TRAINING

Certified Defense Financial Manager (CFDM) Tableau Desktop I, II, III and Visual Analytics Oracle 12c Standard Query Language (SQL) Lean Six Sigma Green Belt